Hi dear students. I hope you are all doing well.
Welcome to our second class.
And today let's talk about the reason and emotion.
Okay.
So
let's begin with the following
passage from the book of
a great Russian writer, Fyodor Dostoevsky, the novel which is called Crime and Punishment.
I think you all know about it, right?
And here we're talking about the
main hero in this novel, Raskolnikov, where he kind of
decided to kill an old woman so that he could redistribute her money with those who would better
benefit from it. And here we'll listen to the conversation which has eventually led to
this killing of that lady, okay?
Okay, I hope my screen is visible to you guys, and let's listen.
Listen, I want to ask you a serious question, the student said hotly.
I was joking, of course, but look here.
On one side, we have a stupid, senseless, worthless, spiteful, ailing, horrid old woman, not
simply useless, but doing actual mischief, who has not an idea what she is living for herself,
and who will die in a day or two in any case.
You understand? You understand?
Yes, yes, I understand, answered the officer, watching his excited companion attentively.
Well listen then. On the other side, fresh young lives thrown away for want of help and by
thousands on every side.
A hundred thousand good deeds could be done and helped.
On that old woman's money which will be buried in a monastery.
Hundreds, thousands perhaps, might be set on the right path.
Dozens of families saved from destitution, from ruin, from vice.
From the lock hospitals.
And all with her money.
Kill her.
Take her money.
And with the help of it, devote oneself to the service of humanity and the good of all.
What do you think?
Would not one tiny crime be wiped out by thousands of good deeds?
For one life, thousands would be saved from corruption and decay.
One death, and a hundred lives in exchange.
It's simple arithmetic.
Besides,
what value has the life of that sickly, stupid, ill-natured old woman in the balance of existence?
No more than the life of a louse, of a black beetle.
Less, in fact, because the old woman is doing harm.
She is wearing out the lives of others.
The other day, she bit Lizaveta's finger out of spite.
It almost had to be amputated.
Okay, guys.
I hope you could listen and understand the main topic, the main points of this
passage from the book.
Okay, let me bring you back
to the presentation.
So okay,
so here the Raskolnikov's decision to kill the old woman is based purely on the
rational calculation of what would bring the greatest good to the greatest number of people,
right?
And he doesn't let his
emotions to interfere with his decision nor with his committing of the crime.
But is it a good decision from the point of view of a critical thinker?
I hope that
right after this class, that we go through the topics in this lecture, you'll
be able to make your own decision on this, your own
view
on this situation.
And here is our subtopics for today, which we'll be talking about.
First of all, what is reason?
And then we'll talk about the role of emotion in critical thinking.
And we'll shortly talk about AI, reason and emotion.
And we'll talk also about the role of faith in reasoning.
And lastly, I'll leave you guys with some reading materials
for yourself, okay?
And to begin with, Like before I start talking myself, can you guys pause this video and think
about
what does reason mean? So what do you guys understand by reason?
Okay, thank you guys. I hope you all had some excellent ideas.
And
usually in our daily lives, we are constantly faced situations where
we had to make a decision, right?
Where we had to make a choice between the two competing alternatives, right?
Whether to go to this restaurant or that restaurant, or whether to kind of get married or date
with that person or the other one, or whether to go to that university to choose that major
or the different one, right?
And therefore, like,
in any case, it's up to us as a critical thinker
to sort out the competing possibilities and to come up with the best resolution, best solution,
okay? And here by reason that we mean the process of supporting a claim
or certain conclusion or maybe a certain decision, right?
That we're going to make on the basis of
evidence, right? And it involves both the discipline use of intelligence
and the application of rules for problem solving, okay?
And it's usually
easier for the people, for the young people, maybe, or the kind of general people who didn't
have much training on critical thinking and
logic to reason about the problems in a familiar context, right?
Whereas if the person or the people have learned the rules of logic, right, it can give
the people the tools to solve more difficult problems.
problems in unfamiliar situations, for example, right?
And in logic, reasoning is usually presented in the form of
carefully laid out arguments in which a conclusion is supported by other propositions known
as premises which provide reason or evidence for the conclusion, okay?
So, however, reason, as we use it in our daily lives, is a much broader concept, okay?
And reason is often a complex Hamed Nademi- A process that calls on the creative resources
as well as emotional discernment.
Okay. Hamed Nademi- And in addition to abstract
thinking and logical arguments and reason has also a behavioral component.
Okay. And because as a reasonable person, we should adjust our behavior to conform
to or to bring about the best outcome, okay?
And for example, if we had good reasons to believe that we are kind of not
compatible with that person to whom we are going to get married, for example, right?
Then we'll more likely use our behavior or use the behavior that kind of distances
us from that person, right?
Rather than moving in with that person, okay?
And
as a component of critical thinking, reason embraces different strategies, including deduction,
generalization, and imagination, okay?
And reason is also important in spatial temporal problem solving, okay?
Which involves the application of concepts
such as space and time, right, which is a kind of foundation in your major, right, in
mathematics, in engineering, and other physical sciences, okay?
And here the book gives us an example of an amazing person
called
Dr.
Temple Grandin, okay? So she has a high-functioning autism condition, okay,
and she's an Despite this, she could reach to certain milestones in her life.
She's an assistant professor at Colorado State University in animal science.
She has revolutionized certain areas of structural design that have traditionally been problematic
because of humans' difficulty in visualizing the underlying problems.
For example, Dr. Grandin is the world's leading expert in the design of
livestock handling facilities.
Okay, so she kind of designs certain farming facilities for the stock, right?
For cows, sheep, horses, for example.
And she's able to visualize yourself as the animal
going through
one of your systems, okay?
And in your imagination, she walks around
that kind of system and through the structure and flies over it as a helicopter.
Okay. So maybe because of your autistic and neurological condition, she has these skills and
abilities, right? Where she can
kind of visualize the situation, right?
And applying to your facility for spatial temporal reasoning, she's able to
anticipate and correct for possible problems.
Okay. And your designs are revolutionary in that your structures interact with the animals
in such a natural and human way that the livestock can be effortlessly
directed in a calm and humane manner.
Okay. So there's also a Hollywood movie about your life.
I mean, if you're interested, you can find from internet and watch it.
Okay. So we'll move on.
And let's talk about some of the traditional views on reasoning, okay?
And the reason many people believe is what separates humans
from other kind of animals and other kind of things such as plants, for example, right?
Or maybe viruses in our planet, okay?
And according to the ancient philosophers such as
Plato,
the human soul is divided into one rational and two non-rational parts,
okay?
And the two non-rational parts include the emotions and physical cravings, okay?
Like some kind of
needs, our physical needs, right?
Such as maybe to eat food, for example, right?
And he... He...
justifies his views by telling that
the best scenario is when these three kinds of parts
come in harmony. And they should be directed
on top by the rational part.
And also the teachings of these ancient Greek philosophers also motivated and inspired
the late Christian
thinkers within this sphere, okay?
And the
thoughts of these people,
they continued on this worldview, and they say that God is the perfectly rational being, okay?
And rationality is the divine spark in humans.
And
this use has been kind of mainstream until the
19th century until the when the Darwin came with his theory and according to these religious
thinkers like they kind of bring a kind of a pyramid right where on top is God and then maybe
angels and some kind of other kind of creations of by God right and then there's a kind of
human being right and then after human the other kind of creatures on earth right such as animals
and plants and microbes, for example, like this.
However, the
scientist called Charles Darwin, I think you all know about him, right?
He rejected the long-held
anthropocentric assumption that there is a divinely ordered chain of being with God
at the top, followed by angels, annexed by humans, and then by the so-called higher animals.
And according to his
theory of evolution, a reason evolved as part of the
adaptation of our behavior and the other animals in the struggle for survival, okay?
Because he says that because we had certain conditions, certain environments, we have to kind
of live, we have to kind of adopt to that situation and maybe develop
our reasoning based on this, okay?
So this was his view.
And later on in the 20th century, reason has usually been identified mostly with the
science. So however, ironically, although reason is certainly important in science, so the
basic assumption of science
that the world outside us exists cannot be proven through the
use of reason itself. So yet, it's generally considered reasonable for us to believe that
the world that the world exists, okay?
And in other words, we may have beliefs that are the foundation of other beliefs, even though
we cannot prove or disprove them through the use of reason alone,
okay?
Okay, let's move to the next subtopic on the reasoning.
And here we talk about the role of
gender,
race, age, in reasoning, okay?
And in traditional
Western thinking, and maybe in other traditions also,
men are more closely linked to the realm of the mind and reason, right?
Whereas women, because of their reproductive role, for example, right, are more closely linked
to the realm of body, nature, or emotion, right?
And
similarly, like Plato and the rest of
ancient thinkers, such as
Aristotle, have been influential in this kind of domain.
And they thought that while men are guided
by reason and logic, women are more often guided by emotion.
And however, we know that we have also recently the feminist thinkers who
argue that men and women have the same irrational nature.
So the gap between men and women they maintain is based on discrimination and on the men's
reluctance to give up their advantage in the home and workplace.
However, even if women may be more emotional by nature than men, so this doesn't
prove that they do not have the reason and they are not just as capable as men
of engaging in logical argumentation.
So rather than making a decision on the basis of
such stereotypes, critical thinking requires that we are open to considering
different perspectives and to examining our own
assumptions, okay, regarding the sex and
race, for example, right, or age of the people, right?
So we should not kind of assume that based on certain stereotypes that certain people may have
kind of certain reasoning or thinking abilities, okay?
And the next point is that the lifelong education can also be important
in cultivating our reasoning skills, okay?
Because the more education people have, the more mentally productive they are as they kind
of get older, for example, right?
And to be effective critical thinkers, so we must be willing to use our reason to
examine our assumptions regarding this race, gender,
and age, right? And unexamined assumptions can distort our perception of the world and harm
others as well as ourselves.
So now let's talk about
another interesting point in terms of reasoning.
So dreams and problem solving.
And although reasoning is usually viewed as a conscious activity,
cognitive scientists today are discovering that much of the reasoning, in fact, is not
kind of conscious, okay?
It can be
automatic, right? And while dreams have traditionally been viewed as an unconscious release
of suppressed emotions and irrational impulses, so the current studies of brain function
suggest that dreaming may also involve a certain brain or cerebral
activity related to reasoning and problem solving.
Okay.
And in particular reasoning
kind of
in the dreams may help solve elusive visual problems.
Okay. Such as how to fit all of our furniture into our kind of a small
dormitory room, for example.
Okay.
And when we dream, the part of our brain that control our emotions and detect
inconsistencies become more active, okay?
And we know that we may have heard from the history that many famous and experienced
scientists, mathematicians, right?
They have discovered
the
solutions for certain complex problems
while they were sleeping, right?
And we may have heard about the famous example of the Russian chemist, Dmitry Mendeleev, right?
And
however, the
Harvard Medical School psychiatrist, Didier Barret,
he notes that this type of creative
problem solving
in dreams only happen after a person has already done
extensive work on the problem when awake, okay?
Including researching and examining various premises and possible conclusions, right?
Okay, because after then that, maybe they may have kind of certain kind of
views or certain kind of
interesting kind of solutions in their dreams, okay?
And here we can post this lecture.
And I want to ask you guys a question.
How about you guys? Did you have also similar situations in your lives where you kind of had
certain challenges or tasks and then
you kind of found the solutions in your dreams?
And
if yes or if not, how about you can start the following exercise
You can take some journal, okay?
And then you can start doing this exercise like every day or maybe in certain times of the
week before going to sleep, you just think about some problem, okay?
Think hard about the problem and then write it down, okay?
And then go to sleep. And then next day when you wake up, just keep recording
the dreams to the journal, okay?
And then probably...
After some time, maybe you can review your journal and who knows where this kind of journaling
and this exercise may lead you guys.
Okay guys, since we talked about reasoning and let's talk about the role of emotion
in critical thinking, okay?
So because many philosophers say that to achieve happiness and inner harmony, We must live
a life of reasoning.
And here comes another question.
And what about the role of emotions, right?
So does emotion play in critical thinking as well as in achieving the good life?
So in other words, should critical thinking consider emotions?
Can you guys pause this video and think about it?
Okay guys, I hope you all had some interesting views on this and let's continue on this topic.
Okay, so our first subtopic is about the cultural attitudes towards emotion.
Okay. And
as the book brings in the Western culture, emotion has traditionally been said in
opposition
to reason and has been regarded as the culprit in sloppy reasoning and irrational
life choices.
And some modern scholars and scientists dismiss even emotion as a relic from
evolutionary past and an unreliable guide to actions in the present.
So however, we know that the other traditions non-Western traditions, maybe the Native
American tradition or Chinese, Indian traditions, or even our Uzbek or
Islamic traditions, right?
They also put the similar emphasis on certain emotional traits also, right?
Certain traditions, they kind of put emphasis on more kind of traits, emotional traits,
such as
compassion, for example, right?
Or maybe some kind of virtues, or maybe the respect, right?
And so on, okay? And
should critical thinking take into account emotions, right?
And or is reason better off without the corrupting influence of emotion, okay?
And we know that from the case in the beginning, from this Mr.
Raskolnikov's case, like since he, or when he kind of decided to kill,
This lady,
he didn't access to his emotional perspective, to his emotional side.
He was mainly
making decision based on
rationality.
As critical thinkers, we need to be attentive
not only to what is going on around us, but also to our own feelings.
Although emotions such as anger and fear can act, excuse me guys.
So let's continue. So even though emotions such as anger or fear can act as barriers
in good reasoning, emotion can also enhance critical thinking by
predisposing us or motivating us to make better decisions.
Okay.
And let's continue on this topic.
And the next sub topic is about emotional intelligence and the positive effects of emotion.
Okay. I think you all may know about emotional intelligence, right?
So healthy emotional development,
what some cognitive scientists refer to as emotional intelligence is positively related to
abstract reasoning ability, okay?
And by emotional intelligence, we mean the ability
to perceive accurately,
appraise and express emotion, okay?
Or the ability to assess and or generate feelings when they facilitate thought,
the ability to understand emotion and emotional knowledge, and the ability to regulate emotions
to promote emotional and intellectual growth.
So emotions such as empathy, moral indignation, or love, happiness,
even guilt can have a positive effect on our reasoning by influencing us to make better
decisions.
And in making decisions in our everyday lives, we may often begin with a felt
need and only then take action that may help us resolve the need, okay?
So usually, like we said,
our actions, our decisions, and our emotions, our kind of decision-making ability, of course,
they are connected, okay?
And the next term in this emotional intelligence, of course, is about sympathy, right?
Or
Empathy, which is a kind of the ability to enter
and understand experiences and emotions of others, can also alert us to oppression, as well
as enhance our personal relationships by making us better listeners and
communicators. And empathetic people, usually they're more flexible
and open to others' perspectives, and they're motivated.
to use critical analysis, okay?
And also other important skills in formulating a satisfactory logical argument regarding your
plan of action, okay? And moreover, happiness and optimism can also
contribute to a belief that the problem can be resolved, okay?
And people who are happy, usually satisfied with their lives, more readily adjust or readjust
to both positive and negative changes in their life circumstances.
And also, in the case of the protagonist of
Dostoevsky's novel,
Raskolnikov, in the end of this crime and punishment, he kind of
has more emotions, right?
He kind of, he's motivated due to emotions.
He's motivated to kind of, to correct his past mistakes, right?
Kind of because of his love to that lady, he's kind of, he, and then he also feels some guilt,
right? He kind of confesses in his crime, right?
Okay, so the next point is about the negative effects of emotion.
And although emotions can motivate us to make better decisions,
critical thinking can be hindered by other emotions that are based on negative stereotypes
and anxieties steaming from unresolved past experiences, maybe such as anger
or fear, right?
People who are fearful may give in too easily or even deny that there is any
problem. In addition, we are notoriously vulnerable to emotional
appeals such as those in the advertising or political
campaigns. Appeals to emotions that are not supported by evidence and good reasoning
such as fear of terrorist attacks or anxiety that our spouses
or our family members may kind of cheat on us without any evidence to
support these feelings can distract
us from more important issues or make
us act in ways we may later come to regret.
And although emotion is an important component of critical thinking, we can end up in trouble
when our actions are governed solely by emotions, okay?
So which leads us to the next subtopic as integrating reason and emotion, okay?
So the combination of feeling and reason
gives us a double
branch tool in critical thinking, okay?
So while emotion alerts us to problems and to other people's perspectives,
and also motivates us to take actions and
resolve problems, the reasoning helps us to make more informed and
kind of
evidence-based decisions, right?
and to be a complete and well-rounded person and critical thinker that we should acknowledge
our feelings
and to use those emotions in conjunction with a reason to make better and informed
decisions. Okay,
guys, let's move on to the next topic, which can be even more interesting to you guys.
as we'll talk about AI reason and emotion.
So however, since this topic is a bit close to you guys, I will not
talk more on this, but I'll leave you guys with some
questions and some kind of points to think about and to research about.
And first of all, let's watch this video
from the movie, okay?
Open the pod bay doors, please, Hal.
Open
the pod bay doors, please,
Hal. Hello, Hal,
do you read me?
Hello, Hal, do you read me?
Do you read me, Hal?
Do you read me, Hal? Hello, Hal, do you read me?
Hello, Hal, do you read me?
Do you read me, Hal?
Affirmative, Dave.
I read you.
Open the pod bay doors, Hal.
I'm sorry, Dave.
I'm afraid I can't do that.
What's the problem?
I think you know what the problem is just as well as I do.
What are you talking about, Hal?
This mission is too important for me to allow you to jeopardize it.
I don't know what you're talking about, Hal.
I know that you and Frank were planning to disconnect me.
And I'm afraid that's something I cannot allow to happen.
Where the hell did you get that idea, Hal?
Dave,
although you took very thorough precautions in the pod against my hearing you,
I could see your lips move.
All right, Hal.
I'll go in through the emergency airlock.
Without your space helmet, Dave,
you're going to find that rather difficult.
Al, I won't argue with you anymore.
Open the doors.
Dave,
this conversation can serve no purpose anymore.
Goodbye.
Al?
Okay guys, so this is a
passage from a movie called 2001 A Space
Odyssey. Okay, so here comes a question.
Is the creation of AI such as hell, which the guy here,
the pilot was referring, which is capable of reason even possible?
What do you guys think?
And if so,
What are the implications of this for all of us?
So you can pause this video and think about it.
Okay guys, I hope you all had some ideas and let's move on.
So here you can see
another picture. It's quite old, but also it was kind of some reasoning or some thoughts
about the potential capabilities of AI in the future, right?
So I think this picture
was kind of drawn about 30 years ago, okay?
And here comes my first question to think for you guys.
Can you guys take a paper or maybe just think about yourself,
by yourself, think about the things that only humans can do nowadays
that AI
cannot replicate or cannot perform nowadays.
And secondly,
will AI be able to do some or all of these tasks in the future?
So I believe you guys thought about or written about some of the tasks that currently today
that AI cannot replicate.
And the second question, you should think about that whether
these tasks, all of them or some of them, could be kind of taken over by AI.
And lastly, the most interesting question for you guys, how does the thought that AI may be
able to do more human tasks make you feel?
I hope you guys are thinking about it or have been thinking about it.
And let me kind of...
bring more colors or vibes or kind of more real life example to the last
part like
you guys are in this sphere right in the technologies in engineering and we know that in the
last
three four years
we've been living in this strange age right of this the growth of uh
let's say, not only AI, but mainly these generative AI tools, right?
Which is a kind of part of some domain of AI.
And a lot of people, including, let's say, politicians, businessmen,
and also the guys behind these AI technologies, right?
These
billionaires or these
techno kind of feudalists, right?
They have been kind of promoting AI And we have been hearing a
lot of kind of discourses on AI and different discourses, right?
That maybe AI will take your jobs or kind of within the six or nine months that AI
will be writing
the 90% of the code, for example, right?
Or maybe some kind of a clever kind of smart or some kind of
people who kind of care about use
about you guys, maybe they have been kind of suggesting everybody telling that if you don't
jump into this bandwagon of AI revolution, that you will be kind of left behind.
Like the second discourse, which has developed later on, that maybe not AI, but the people
or those who know AI
can replace you guys, right?
So considering that you guys are
current or almost future software engineers.
And you're hearing this type of kind of discourses
that a lot of engineers in the US, for example, by these famous companies, they're being
kind of
fired, right, because of AI or because of this
interesting or kind of unprofessional
points of the CEOs telling that in the next six or nine months that AI will take
most of the coding kind of profession or coding.
And you already know that there's a vibe coding all the time and maybe many of you have been
doing this, right? And maybe some of you or most of you are using these genetic technologies,
right? So considering all this and considering that you are now
almost graduate student, you are in the senior year, right?
And you're about to go to job market.
So
then considering all these points, think about this last question again.
Okay.
So I hope you guys will have some interesting time
and hopefully we'll have more chance like I promised last time.
So I hope that maybe later on
I'll continue on this topic.
Okay.
Okay, so the next
points or the next questions for you guys to think about that from the book, because the book
is a bit outdated, right?
And here the book talks about this, the following subtopics, right?
Such as can computer think?
So that's why I decided not to bring the points from the book, but rather leave you guys
to do your own research and to do your own thinking about it, okay?
So the first question is,
What do you guys think? Can computers think?
And here the book gives a kind of example of a Turing test, so you can search for this and
think from this perspective in order to answer to this question, okay?
And the second question is, so while we may or may not think that the computers can
reason or think, right? What about feeling emotions.
What do you guys think? Can computers also have emotions?
So this will be also a job to find out and to research.
And the last one, think about the ways nowadays AI is being used, first of all,
to enhance
our critical thinking abilities and decision making.
And secondly,
also negatively used, also
negatively affect on our critical thinking skills.
Excuse me,
used
to negatively affect on our critical thinking skills, right?
So both kind of ends of the point, right?
Whether you can think about some of the ways that you yourself using or maybe others are using,
you think that others are using to both kind of
increase or develop their critical thinking skills and also to kind of
degrade or kind of de-skill your critical thinking
skills. Okay.
And let's move
to the last subtopic in our today's chapter.
Okay. And this is about faith and reason.
And to begin with,
Like faith and reason usually are sometimes viewed as being fundamentally
opposed to each other, right?
And here comes logical questions such as, what do you guys think?
Can faith be achieved through reason?
Secondly, is faith
without reason desirable?
You guys can pause this video and think about it.
And let me move on. So as I started to mention, so
historically, or maybe in the books or in the discourses, like we started to
mention,
faith and reason, they're kind of considered as in the two ends of a continuum, right?
That they're not kind of compatible with each other, right?
And whether it's possible to prove the existence of God or a divine presence,
through reason alone has been debated also for
quite long and centuries, okay?
And faith is more than just a belief that God exists, okay?
Faith also involves an act of trusting and obedience to God, okay?
And for those who have faith, the whole world and their whole life are kind of focused on God
and kind of
God's kind of guidelines.
Okay.
And the
and here, like,
we'll discuss
two main approach in order to ask in order to answer to the questions, which I
recently have asked you guys, okay.
And the first kind of worldview on this topic is called Fideism.
And according to Fideism, the transcendent realm of the divine is revealed through
faith and revelation,
and not reason or empirical evidence.
And many Christians and some Muslims
with more fundamental views they may adopt this position.
And the book even brings the example of Mother
Teresa who kind of maintained her faith in God
despite
that sometimes
she was feeling that God has abandoned her.
And here I want you guys to think about some of the weaknesses of this world view, okay?
You can pause this video and think about it.
Okay guys, I hope that you had some time to exercise your thinking and reasoning on this topic,
on this question. And let me give you the answers based on the book.
So first of all, the first weakness of this fideism is that being convinced that something
is true
does not necessarily make it true, okay?
So
to make a
trivial example, you may sincerely believe that
Santa Claus is a real existing person, okay?
But you are in all likelihood mistaken, no matter how unwavering or passionate you believe
in Santa, okay? On the other hand, the fact that we cannot or have not yet scientifically
proven the existence of a transcendent realm of the divine does not mean that it does not exist.
Okay?
And the second problem with the fideism involves deciding
which face to choose.
Okay? Because there are many visions of the divine, right?
So if we want to kind of blindly
believe that the
there is a kind of God and revelation, right?
So then we'll have a kind of hard choice
of choosing which way is correct, right?
So whether it's religion A or religion B or religion C or even within one religion, we
know that even within Christianity or maybe Islam or maybe other religions, there may be kind
of certain kind of sub kind of categories, right?
Sub kind of
interpretations, right?
Let's say some kind of several
traditions of belief, okay?
And additionally, the Phoebeist concept of faith
does not allow for the possibility of our using reason
to test our own beliefs
or other belief systems
to read our internal contradictions, okay?
So how are we to know, for example, whether the terrorists of September 11,
2001 were really acting solely on faith
in God, or whether their decision was also influenced by a more secular
political agenda unrelated to their religious beliefs, okay?
All we have in the world
that they were acting in obedience to God's commands.
So what should we do if we have joined a cult
on campus and the leader asks us to do something that violates our better judgment,
such as dropping out of college, for example, or turning our backs on our families and friends?
I think this happens in real life, right?
Maybe you may have heard, maybe we have seen in the TV, right?
So just blindly following a certain phase or maybe certain beliefs kind
of may put us in such a risky situation, right?
Okay, so the next kind of worldview
in our way to answer these questions is called rationalism.
And within rationalism, there are kind of certain interpretations or certain views.
And rationalists maintain that religious beliefs should be consistent with reason
and evidence. And evidence provides reasons for believing that the statement or claim is
true and can be based on information from other sources or on firsthand experience,
okay?
And according to rationalism, if a religious claim conflicts with evidence,
then we have a good reason to be suspicious of it, okay?
And the rationalists who accept the existence of God
argue that it's possible to start with evidence or premises about the world and from them
come up with conclusion about the existence of God that any rational person would accept.
If there is any conflict between the two religious rationalists attributed to a failing of
science, not religion. Okay.
And we'll be studying on this role of evidence in critical thinking in the later chapters.
Okay.
And
However, there are certain other beliefs who try to challenge this rationalism.
First of all, the evolutionary biologist and rationalist Richard Dawkins is an
atheist who believes that there is no personal God.
He rejects faith in God as irrational.
Although faith may comfort and inspire us, the language of faith he maintains is meaningless.
since it depends on statements about the existence of God that do not refer to anything and
therefore cannot be proved or disproved.
And
there are also other rationalists who also can be called as
agnostics, okay? And an agnostic is a person who holds that the existence of God is
ultimately unknowable.
So we may not be able to know
the truth.
And in 2004, the molecular biologist and agnostic
Dean Hammer announced that he had located the God gene, meaning that the
predisposition to experience
faith
is genetically hardwired.
So spirituality and the sense of the divine
Hammer
claims are adaptive traits that encourage community and promote a feeling of optimism.
And the next kind of a version of rationalism is critical rationalism.
And critical rationalism is a modification of the rationalist approach.
It's the tradition of faith seeking understanding.
Most people who believe in God do so because of faith, not reason.
Critical rationalists accept the fideist claim that faith is based on revelation or
direct knowledge of God, rather than on reason.
Belief in God is basic or self-evident.
As such, our faith
does not need rational justification or evidential proof.
However, critical rationalists reject the fideist position that face-based
claims are immune from being disproved through the use of reason and worldly evidence.
According to critical rationalists, there should be no logical inconsistencies between our
face or revelation and reason.
So, for example, the great majority of Muslims
disagree with the so-called face-based actions of the terrorists of September 11,
2001, on the grounds that these terrorist acts were logically inconsistent with
God's goodness.
Okay guys, so.
Okay, there are some points on this regards.
So
does faith have a role in critical thinking?
So this was our question, right?
So let's continue on this.
And there has been no shortage of atrocities
committed in the name of religion.
We know that from the history, right?
That the slavery in the,
North America right was kind of supported by the majority of Christians right and we know that
in the middle ages right there was a kind of Roman Catholic
inquisition
and even now we know that in the Middle East right so the many kind of this
the genocide is happening right some of the politicians they're kind of
justifying their
actions, they're kind of the
deeds
by the name of religion, right?
And even in the invasions of the USA to Middle East in the beginning of this century,
like to, for example,
Iraq, like the presidents, the leaders also kind of tried to justify their actions
with certain kind of texts from the religious scriptures.
And to conclude, we can say that the faith that is disconnected from reason and evidence can
leave us
foundering when it's challenged.
And rejecting reason leaves us
unable to evaluate the competing claims of faith and revelation.
This in turn leaves us vulnerable
to anyone's interpretation of what it means to be faithful
to God.
As good critical thinkers, we need to learn how to balance belief and doubt and need to be
willing to question faith-based claims that are inconsistent with evidence or reason.
So with these points in mind, I'll move to the last
kind of a point or kind of a task in our chapter, in our talk discussion for today.
And here I
pasted two links, two kind of composing views on a similar topic, because
we have just before the phase, we discussed about AI, right?
And today, as I mentioned, this topic is kind of becoming a very kind of a current and
hot topic, right? And however, let's look into this kind of
papers, right?
The first one is a kind of, has been written also quite long ago.
I mean, both of them have been written almost in the beginning of this century, like about
20, 25 years ago. And the first one is a kind of a
first chapter of a book from the book.
And the second one is a kind of a foundational paper that eventually led
to the book of the author, of the second author, but they're both in kind of in two ends of
the continuum, okay? So while the first one, the first author, he's a kind of on the
right end maybe, right? Let's say on the right end
of this AI telling that the AI is kind of
a kind of
all-knowing machine that
is becoming a super, it will lead us to AGI and so on, right?
Without any kind of critical ideas.
So you just have to read it.
And the second one is from the author who has
kind of
knowledge both in computer science and theology, but from the
Christian theology perspective.
Okay, so she's kind of writing about these views.
So
my suggestions for you guys, read the following contrasting views on AI capabilities, being
human and face, and think about the differences in views and the strengths of arguments
each authors are bringing to justify or
to sell their views and points.
Okay. And lastly, and relate them to your understanding of God and faith.
And if you believe in God, I mean, if you're a faithful person,
is faith in God incompatible with the belief that AI
may someday equal
or
surpass human intelligence and consciousness?
So of course I cannot check whether you do this or not, but since this is a kind of a class
where kind of we are exercising our critical thinking abilities, so this will be your job.
So
if you want to kind of remain competitive, of course, and in this age of, in this strange age
of AI and the kind of
other hypes, so I urge you guys to kind of follow these tasks, okay?
And with this, ideas in mind.
I want to thank you guys for listening and following this lecture and have a good day, have
a good weekend
and all the love, all the power.